Finding Aid for Louis Charles Karpinski papers, 1838-1889 and 1901-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Louis Charles Karpinski papers 1838-1889, 1901-1955
Karpinski, Louis Charles, 1878-1956.
3 linear feet
851725 Aa 2
Professor of mathematics at University of Michigan. Correspondence, printed materials and miscellanea relating to his research in mathematics and the history of science, his interest in collecting historical manuscripts, maps, and rare books, and his personal affairs; also photograph.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from Professor Karpinski (donor no. 389 ) in 1949 and from Mrs. Paul Adams (donor no. 3999 ) in 1963.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Dr. Louis Charles Karpinski was born August 5, 1878 in Rochester, N.Y. He received his bachelor's degree in 1901 from Cornell University and was awarded a PhD degree by the University of Strasbourg, Germany in 1903.
He taught at Berea College, Kentucky, from 1897 to 1899 and at Oswego Normal College, 1903-04. He was in charge of the mathematics department at the Chautauquan Institute, Chautauqua, N.Y., from 1905 to 1907. He was a teachers' college fellow and university extension lecturer at Columbia University in 1909-10.
Dr. Karpinski became instructor of mathematics at the University of Michigan in 1904, assistant professor in 1914 and professor of mathematics in 1919, a post he held until his retirement, Aug. 5, 1948.
Dr. Karpinski was a member of the American Mathematical Society, the Mathematical Association of America and the Historical Science Society. He was author of several books on mathematics, some of them in German. These include The History of Arithmetic and Unified Mathematics. He died in 1956.
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Collected letters of historical personages; Mathematics and cartographical interests; Collecting historical documents (with materials collected by LCK); and miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Ipswich (Mass.); Karpinski, Louis Charles, 1878-1956.; Mathematics.; Roads--Massachusetts--Ipswich.; Science.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mathematics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Karpinski, Louis Charles, 1878-1956.
Contributors:
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Breasted, James Henry, 1865-1935.; Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938.; Cajori, Florian, 1859-1930.; Cameron, William John, 1879-1955.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Frost, William G. (William Goodell), 1854-1938.; Fulton, James Street, 1904-1997; Hamlin, Hannibal, 1809-1891.; Harrison, William Henry, 1773-1841.; Haskins, Charles Homer, 1870-1937.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), b. 1858.; Lamont, Daniel Scott, 1851-1905.; Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999.; Nast, Thomas, 1840-1902.; Pogo, Alexander, 1893-; Poole, Reginald Lane, 1857-1939.; Sankey, Ira David, 1840-1908.; Sarton, George, 1884-1956.; Shryock, Richard Harrison, 1893-1972.; Singer, Charles Joseph, 1876-1960.; Singer, Dorothea Waley.; Smith, David Eugene, 1860-1944.; Spaulding, Thomas M. (Thomas Marshall), b. 1882.; Stevens, Thaddeus, 1792-1868.; Straight, Michael Whitney.; Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968.; Thorndike, Lynn, 1882-1965.; Uspensky, J. V. (James Victor), b. 1883.; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes letters from Karpinski to his parents (1901-1903) written from Europe while he was a student there. In addition, there is professional correspondence relating to his scholarly interests in mathematics, the history of science, cartography, and the collecting of historical manuscripts and rare books. Correspondents include: Randolph G. Adams, Charles A. Beard, James H. Breasted, George L. Burr, Florian Cajori, W. J. Cameron, William L. Clements, J. Fulton, Charles H. Haskins, Francis W. Kelsey, Ashley Montague, Alexander Pogo, R. L. Poole, George Sarton, Richard Shryock, Charles Singer, Dorothea Waley Singer, David E. Smith, Michael Straight, Arthur H. Sulzberger, Lynn Thorndike, J. Uspensky, and Henry A. Wallace.
  - 1901-1905 (Box 1)
    (folder no.1)
  - 1906-1910 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 2)
  - 1911-1915 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 3)
  - 1916-1920 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 4)
  - 1921-1930 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 5)
  - 1931-1940 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 6)
  - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 7)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 8)
  - 1947 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 9)
  - 1948 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 10)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 11)
  - 1950 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 12)
  - 1951 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 13)
  - 1952 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 14)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 15)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 16)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 17)
  - undated (Box 1)
    (folder no. 18)
- Collected letters of historical personages
  The Collected letters of historical personages included letters of Hannibal Hamlin, Daniel S. Lamont, Ira Sankey, and Thaddeus Stevens.
  - Hannibal Hamlin October 28, 1889 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 19)
  - Daniel S. Lamont March 29, 1886 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 20)
  - Ira Sankey July 24, 1896 (Box 1)
    (folder no. 21)
  - Thaddeus Stevens March 6, 1841 (letter addressed to President William Henry Harrison), May 15, 1864, August 13, 1865, circa August 16, 1866, May 20, 1867, August 27, 1867, December 25, 1867 (Box 1)
    (folder 22)
- Mathematics and cartographical interests
  The Mathematics and cartographical interests series relates in part to his interest in the development of arithmetic and the mathematics of the Middle and Far East.
  - Book Rare Arithmetica (1908) by David Eugene Smith with extensive notations by LCK (Box 1)
  - Book The Hindu-Arabic Numerals (1911) by David Eugene Smith and Louis Charles Karpinski with extensive notations by LCK (Box 1)
  - Book History of Arithmetic (1925) by Louis Charles Karpinski with extensive notations by LCK (Box 1)
  - Book Bibliography of Egyptian Mathematics with special references to the Rhind Mathematical Papyrus (1927) by Raymond Clare Archibald (Box 1)
  - Thesis of Irby Coghill Nichols (University of Michigan): "A Comparative Study of Fractions of the Early Treatises on the Hindu Art of Reckoning" (Box 2)
  - Thesis of Sister Mary Thomas à Kempis Kloyda (University of Michigan) 1938 "Linear and Quadratic Equations 1550-1660" (Box 2)
  - History of mathematics materials (Box 2)
    (folder 23)
  - Mathematics miscellaneous, 8 folders (Box 2)
    (folder nos. 24-31)
  - Map research miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 2)
    (folder nos. 32-34)
- Collected historical documents
  - Road assessment of Ipswich, Massachusetts 1838 (Box 3)
    (folder no. 35)
  - Civil War miscellanea (Box 3)
    (folder no. 35.1)
  - Rare materials collected by Karpinski, 3 folders (Box 3)
    (folder nos. 36-38)
- Miscellaneous
  - List of publications by Karpinski (Box 3)
    (folder no. 39)
  - Lists and miscellanea pertaining to rare books, 3 folders (Box 3)
    (folder no. 40-42)
  - The Dearborn Independent
    (LCK wrote several articles for this newspaper)
    - 1924 (Box 3)
      (folder no. 43)
    - 1925 (Box 3)
      (folder no. 44)
    - Undated and miscellaneous printed materials (Box 3)
      (folder no. 45)
  - Clippings and miscellanea (Box 3)
    (folder no. 46)
  - Miscellanea; include postcards (Box 3)
    (folder no. 47)
  - Miscellaneous booklets, etc. (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
Index to Selective Correspondents
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.
June 9, 1927 (folder 5)
Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.
June 17, 1933 (folder 6)
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.
Nov. 8, 1926 (folder 5)
Breasted, James Henry, 1865-1935.
Jan. 14, 1914 (folder 3)
Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938.
Jan. 16, 1913, Apr. 29, 1913 (folder 3)
Cajori, Florian, 1859-1930.
Oct 24, 1919 (folder 4), June 24, 1928, July 3, 1928 (folder 5)
Cameron, William John, 1879-1955.
Jan. 7, 1927 (folder 5)
Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.
Jan. 12, 1927 (folder 5)
Frost, William G. (William Goodell), 1854-1938.
Jan. 4, 1902, June 25, 1903, Feb. 12, 1904 (folder 1), Feb. 6, 1912 (folder 3)
Fulton, James Street, 1904-
Mar. 3, 1943 (folder 7)
Hamlin, Hannibal, 1809-1891.
Oct 28, 1889 (folder 9)
Harrison, William Henry, 1773-1841.
Mar. 6, 1841 (folder 22)
Haskins, Charles Homer 1870-1937.
Jan. 2, 1912, Nov. 12, 1914, Feb. 1, 1915 (folder 3), May 21, 1926 (folder 5)
Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), 1858.
Mar. 9, 1912 (folder 3)
Lamont, Daniel Scott, 1851-1905.
Mar. 29, 1886 (folder 20)
Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999.
Mar. 31, 1943 (folder 7)
Nast, Thomas, 1840-1902.
Mar. 29, 1886 (folder 20)
Pogo, Alexander, 1893-
Apr. 1, 1943, Apr. 26, 1943, Dec. 22, 1943 (folder 7)
Poole, Reginald Lane, 1857-1939.
May 8, 1913, May 9, 1913, Aug. 7, 1913, Apr. 15, 1914, July 16, 1914, Sept. 4, 1914 (folder 3)
Sankey, Ira David, 1840-1908.
July 24, 1896 (folder 21)
Sarton, George, 1884-1956.
June 23, 1928 (folder 5), Aug. 21, 1936 (folder 6), Jan. 17, 1943, Apr. 26, 1943, Nov. 19, 1944 (folder 7)
Shryock, Richard Harrison, 1893-1972.
Jan. 5, 1943, Jan. 20, 1943, Jan. 22, 1943, Jan. 26, 1943 (folder 7)
Singer, Charles Joseph, 1876-1960.
Oct. 15, 1930 (folder 5), Dec. 1, 1934 (folder 6)
Singer, Dorothea (Waley)
Aug. 27, 1927, Jan. 2, 1930 (folder 5), Nov. 19, 1948 (folder 10)
Smith, David Eugene, 1860-1944.
June 3, 1905, Sept. 23 1905 (folder 1), Apr. 7, 1909, Apr. 19, 1909, Apr. 27, 1909 (folder 2), Mar. 9 1912, Nov. 11, 1912, Mar. 26, 1914 (folder 3), Nov. 14, 1923, May 7, 1924 (folder 6), Jan. 21, 1932, undated 1932 (folder 6), Nov. 10, 19?? (folder 18)
Spaulding, Thomas M. (Thomas Marshall), 1882.
Jan. 18, 1940, Jan. 27, 1940, Feb. 22, 1940, Mar. 2, 1940, Mar. 30, 1940, May 15, 1940 (folder 6), Oct. 22, 1941 (folder 7), Dec. 9, 19?? (folder 18)
Stevens, Thaddeus, 1792-1868.
Mar 6, 1841, May 15, 1864, Aug. 13, 1865, Aug. 16, 1866, May 20, 1867, Aug. 27, 1867, Dec. 25, 1867 (folder 22)
Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968.
Mar. 25, 1943 (folder 7)
Thorndike, Lynn, 1882-1965.
Oct. 17, 1921 (folder 5)
Uspensky, J. V. (James Victor), 1883.
Mar, 27, 1925 (folder 5)
Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.
Feb. 24, 1943 (folder 7)